Guide to the Robert N. Caldwell Correspondence
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Robert N. Caldwell Correspondence
1949-1969.
Caldwell, Robert N., 1908-
1.26 linear ft (3 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0182
4078574
In 1949, New Jersey newspaper editor Robert N. Caldwell began a close friendship with his former professor at Columbia University, Mark van Doren. The two frequently discussed politics, literature, philosophy, and their day-to-day lives. This collection consists of correspondence, between Robert Caldwell and Columbia professor Mark van Doren spanning two decades.
Biographical Note
Robert N. Caldwell first met Mark van Doren in one of his English classes at Columbia University in 1928. Upon graduating in 1932, Caldwell returned to his home state of New Jersey where he joined the staff of a local newspaper, The Record. Sixteen years later, after he had become the managing editor of another local paper The Bayonne Times, Caldwell and van Doren's paths would cross again. A controversy in Bayonne over the transferring of a secondary school teacher, another of van Doren's former students, would spark a letter to the editor from the professor, thus igniting a close friendship and twenty year correspondence.
Just as van Doren lent a friendly ear throughout the Bayonne school board controversy, so too did Caldwell when van Doren and his publications were accused of promoting communism in 1951. The two frequently wrote each other of personal crises as well as triumphs. Also in 1951, van Doren, through the Association of the Alumni of Columbia College, nominated Caldwell for the association's Alexander Hamilton Medal, an award for distinguished service and accomplishment in any field of endeavor.
In 1961, Caldwell returned to The Record and was named its assistant editor in 1967. Robert Caldwell died on May 31, 1973, at the age of 64.
Scope and Content
The Robert N. Caldwell Correspondence consist almost entirely of correspondence between Caldwell and Mark van Doren. The two began their correspondence over local politics, specifically those in Bayonne, NJ, where Caldwell worked as a newspaper editor. As the friendship progressed, topics moved to parenting, philosophy, and literature, with van Doren frequently sharing his poems.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series.
Series I: Letters to Mark van Doren, 1949-1969
Series II: Letters from Mark van Doren, 1949-1969
Series III: Other Correspondence and Clippings, 1951-1969
Selected Related Material at Columbia
Mark van Doren Papers, 1917-1976 Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Subjects
Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Newspaper publishing--New Jersey.; Journalism.; Literature.; Philosophy.; Correspondence.
Gift of Robert N. Caldwell, 1969.
- Series I: Letters to Mark van Doren, 1949-1969
  Series I is comprised of typed carbon copies of Caldwell's letters to van Doren, dating from February 26, 1949 to March 20, 1969
  - 1949 February-1950 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1951 February-March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1951 April-May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1951 June-July (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1951 August-October (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1951 November-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1952 January-March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1952 April-July (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1952 August-December (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1953 January-December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1954 January-1955 December (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1956 January-November (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1957 January-December (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1958 February-1969 March (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series II: Letters from Mark van Doren, 1949-1969
  The second series consists of van Doren's primarily handwritten letters, some with accompanying envelopes, and postcards to Caldwell dating from February 19, 1949 to September 9, 1969.
  - 1949 February-1951 June (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1951 July-1952 May (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1952 June-1954 May (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1954 June-1958 December (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1959 January-1963 December (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1964 January-1969 September (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III: Other Correspondence and Clippings, 1951-1969
  Series III contains miscellaneous correspondence as well as newspaper clippings. There is a postcard from van Doren to Caldwell's daughter, Cathy, and letters from Dorothy and Charlie van Doren, Mark's wife and son, to Caldwell. There is a small collection of correspondence between Caldwell and Verb Gabbert. Finally, there are a variety of newspaper clippings of articles written either about van Doren or by Caldwell.
  - Letters from the van Dorens to the Caldwells, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Verb Gabbert Correspondence, 1951 August-1955 May (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1951-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)